{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Similarities of this speech to Abraham Lincoln’s Gettysburg Address have been noted by scholars, as both praise \"the uniqueness of the State’s commitment to democracy.” The speaker of this address proclaims, “Thus choosing to die resisting, rather than to live submitting, they fled only from dishonor” when referring to a certain group of people. This speech was recorded by Thucydides in his book History of the Peloponnesian War. For ten points, what \"Oration\" was spoken by an Athenian politician to honor the soldiers who perished fighting the Spartans?",
      "answer": [
        "Pericles’s Funeral Oration",
        "equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A leader with this surname was deposed in Operation Fair Play, a coup led by Muhammad Zia-ul-Haq. Following a separatist movement led by Sheikh Mujib, a leader with this surname founded the PPP, or People's Party. A prime minister with this surname was killed in a car bombing in Rawalpindi in 2007. With Indira Gandhi, a prime minister with this surname signed the Shimla Agreement, which established the Line of Control in Kashmir. For ten points, identify this surname shared by Pakistani prime ministers Benazir and Zulfikar Ali.",
      "answer": [
        "Bhutto",
        "Benazir Bhutto",
        "or Zulfikar Ali Bhutto"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This attorney charged that Reuben Crandall's publications instigated slaves to rebel in the leadup to the Snow Riot. Earlier, this man prosecuted Richard Lawrence, who tried to use two malfunctioning firearms to kill Andrew Jackson. This man was detained aboard the HMS Tonnant to negotiate the release of William Beanes, during which time he wrote a poem that mentions \"the shore dimly seen through the mists of the deep.\" For ten points, name this lawyer, who wrote a poem about the shelling of Fort McHenry which later became \"The Star-Spangled Banner.\"",
      "answer": "Francis Scott Key"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1665, public celebrations of this observance were banned under the Mughal emperor Aurangzeb. Guru Gobind Singh extended this observance for Sikhs, adding a three- day-long festival which traditionally includes martial arts demonstrations. In 2016, Pakistan controversially gave localities the power to declare this festival a public holiday. For ten points, name this Hindu “Festival of Love\" that celebrates the arrival of spring and which is often celebrated by people throwing brightly colored powders.",
      "answer": [
        "Holi",
        "Holika Dahan",
        "or Rangwali Holi",
        "or Dol Purnima",
        "or Dhuleti",
        "or Dhulandi",
        "or Ukuli",
        "or Manjal Kuli",
        "or Yaosang",
        "or Shigmo",
        "or Phagwah",
        "or Jajiri"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician was depicted as the \"after\" photo in a cover by the Private Eye with the headline, “World’s First Face Transplant A Success.’” This politician was heavily criticized after labeling another party as “fruitcakes, loonies, and closet racists.” The decision for the United Kingdom to opt out of the European Union led to this politician’s resignation in 2016. For ten points, what Conservative politician preceded Theresa May as prime minister of the United Kingdom?",
      "answer": "David Cameron or David William Donald Cameron"
    },
    {
      "question": "Despite originally being this man's campaign manager, James Garfield jumped him and James G. Blaine as the Republican presidential candidate in 1880. Accusations of bribery led to the belief that this man committed the \"Crime of '73.\" Due to the ineffective Valentine Act in his home state, this man supported a namesake act that involved a certain \"restraint of trade.\" Henry Clayton amended that act named for this Ohio senator, which permits \"innocent monopolies.\" For ten points, identify this namesake of an 1890 Antitrust Act.",
      "answer": [
        "John Sherman",
        "Sherman Antitrust Act of 1890"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The writing on the Pashupati seal found at this site has yet to be deciphered. This site's initial excavation was led by Ernest Mackay, who discovered artworks including the soapstone \"Priest-King'' statue and the bronze \"Dancing Girl\" statuette. This site's Great Granary and Great Bath date from the Third millennium BCE, and this site's name means \"mound of the dead men'' in Sindhi. For ten points, name this archeological site in present- day Pakistan, a major center of the Indus Valley Civilization.",
      "answer": "Mohenjo-daro"
    },
    {
      "question": "Signs protesting this event encouraged residents to “buy no milk.” An editorial by the New York Times dubbed this event the “Nightmare in the Catskills.” Governor Nelson Rockefeller, who declared this event a “disaster zone,” considered sending in the National Guard but was dissuaded by this event’s organizer, John P. Roberts. Carlos Santana, the Killers, and Miley Cyrus were scheduled to perform in a failed revival of this event. For ten points, what landmark 1960s musical festival was held in Bethel, New York?",
      "answer": [
        "Woodstock or Woodstock Music and Art Fair",
        "or Woodstock Rock Festival"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man, who founded and led the National Union of Mineworkers in the 1980s, was implicated in the violent Marikana massacre against striking miners. This Soweto-born politician lost a 1997 presidential election to fellow party member Thabo Mbeki [[mm-BEH- kee]]. In July 2021, this politician deployed the National Guard to the states of Gauteng and KwaZulu-Natal after the arrest of his predecessor, Jacob Zuma, caused riots and looting. For ten points, name this ANC politician and president of South Africa.",
      "answer": "Cyril Ramaphosa or Matamela Cyril Ramaphosa 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    },
    {
      "question": "This state's Nutty Putty Cave was permanently filled in with concrete after John Jones became fatally stuck upside down in a narrow passageway in 2009. 19th century French fur trapper Étienne Provost inspired the name of a city in this state after he followed the Green River to discover this state's largest body of water. One National Park in this state was first homesteaded by Ebenezer Bryce. For ten points, name this western state where in 1928, Bryce Canyon National Park was established, one year before Arches National Park came into being.",
      "answer": "Utah 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At this location's Mormon Row, a structure built by T.A. Moulton has been called \"the most photographed barn in America.\" Menor's Ferry traversed the Snake River in this area, which became a National Park in 1929. Once known as the JY Ranch, the Laurance S. Rockefeller Preserve is located on the southern end of Phelps Lake in this park. For ten points, name this National Park in northwestern Wyoming, located just south of Yellowstone.",
        "answer": [
          "Grand Teton National Park",
          "Grand Tetons"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Most visitors to Grand Teton National Park pass through which Wyoming town, located in a namesake \"hole\" where a ski resort with the same name opened in the 1960s?",
        "answer": [
          "Jackson",
          "Jackson Hole"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An organization comprised of members of this ethnic group was infiltrated by Pinkerton detectives hired by Franklin B. Gowen, and a group known as the AOH advocated for this ethnic group’s rights in Pennsylvania coal mines. Many members of that group, the Ancient Order of Hibernians, also belonged to a secret society of this ethnic group which was infiltrated by James McParland of the Pinkertons. The Molly Maguires were composed of, for ten points, what ethnic group that immigrated to the U.S. in massive numbers following an 1840s potato famine?",
        "answer": "Irish-Americans"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Many nineteenth-century businesses demonstrated their unwillingness to hire Irish-Americans by posting signs with this four-letter acronym that encouraged Irish- Americans to look elsewhere for work.",
        "answer": "NINA or No Irish Need Apply"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nubian soldiers headquartered near this city’s Thika Road may have been the earliest inhabitants of one of its regions that began as a forest settlement. George Whitehouse originally founded this city that served as a depot during the construction of the Uganda Railway. In 2009, a rehousing scheme that was supported by Raila Odinga aimed to clear slums of this city, such as Kibera. In 1950, the East African Trade Unions Congress held a nine-day general strike in this city. For ten points, name this city shared by the Maasai and Kikuyu, the largest city and capital of Kenya.",
        "answer": [
          "Nairobi",
          "Enkare Nairobi"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Kenyan port city was the site of the Portuguese Fort Jesus and came under control of the Omani Imamate in the late seventeenth century? Its namesake \"Tusks\" were built by the British to commemorate a visit by Queen Elizabeth II.",
        "answer": [
          "Mombasa",
          "Mombasa Tusks 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One politician in this country often ended campaign speeches by stating, “I’m different.” A 62-year-old wife of a former president of this country was the frontrunner and eventual winner of this country’s 2021 general election. That woman, Xiomara Castro, is married to this country's former president, Manuel Zelaya. San Pedro Sula was one of the cities heavily affected by a 1998 Category 5 storm that hit this country, Hurricane Mitch. For ten points, name this Central American country that fought the 1960 Soccer War with neighboring El Salvador.",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Honduras",
          "República de Honduras"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In reference to countries like Honduras, which were heavily under the influence of U.S. corporate interests, what American author of \"The Luck of Roaring Camp\" coined the term “banana republic\"?",
        "answer": "O. Henry or William Sydney Porter"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one speech, this man asked “What is the mood of America and of the world toward America today?” A campaign to go “Clean For [this man]\" involved the mass-shaving of beards among his supporters. Due to his anti-Vietnam War stance, this politician surged in the polls following the 1968 Tet Offensive. Like the eventual nominee from his party in that year, this man hailed from Minnesota. For ten points, name this Democrat who lost out to LBJ's preferred candidate, Hubert Humphrey, in the contentious 1968 Democratic National Convention.",
        "answer": "Eugene McCarthy or Eugene Joseph \"Gene\" McCarthy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "McCarthy was a plaintiff in this 1976 Supreme Court case that found election spending limits to be a Constitutional violation.",
        "answer": [
          "Buckley v. Valeo",
          "James L. Buckley, et al. v. Francis R. Valeo, Secretary of the United States Senate, et al"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A set of fortifications along a shore named for these people is detailed in the Notitia Dignitatum. These people faced a confederacy of Obotrites led by Drozko at the Battle of Bornhöved. A group of these people who resided in Bayeux served in the army of Clovis I, and a pillar sacred to the pagan religion of these people was destroyed during the Massacre at Verden. Widukind was a leader of, for ten points, what Germanic group who settled England alongside the Angles?",
        "answer": "Saxons"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The earliest-known mention of the Saxons in writing may have been in this Latin- Egyptian polymath’s Geographia.",
        "answer": [
          "Claudius Ptolemy",
          "Klaudios Ptolemaios 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One product created by this company was named after an inventor, because alleged attempts at “everything else… failed.” That product was the Edison device, which was analyzed in a series of 2015 articles by John Carreyrou. In 2012, Safeway attempted to outfit its stores with products of this company that was founded by a nineteen-year-old who had dropped out of Stanford. SEC fraud charges were levelled against this company’s founder, Elizabeth Holmes, who made exaggerated claims about its blood-testing products. For ten points, identify this healthcare technology company.",
        "answer": "Theranos"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John Carreyrou's article appeared in this periodical which first published the \"Dow Jones Industrial Average\" in 1896.",
        "answer": "The Wall Street Journal"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a triptych named for this concept, the artist painted himself as a grayish figure helping a wounded man to the right of a figure floating above the scene. Figures such as Alekto, Pestilence, and Venus appear in a commentary painting by Peter Paul Rubens titled for the Consequences of [this concept]. In Vasily Vereshchagin's painting titled for The Apotheosis of [this concept], a pile of skulls sits outside the walls of a Central Asian city. For ten points, name this concept, depicted in a 1924 painting by Otto Dix inspired by his experiences in the trenches.",
        "answer": [
          "War",
          "The War",
          "The Apotheosis of War",
          "Consequences of War"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This artist painted a disembodied face whose mouth and eye sockets are filled with identical faces in The Face of War. He represented the horrors of the Spanish Civil War in Soft Construction with Boiled Beans.",
        "answer": [
          "Salvador Dali or Salvador Domingo Felipe Jacinto Dali i Domenech",
          "or 1st Marquis of Dalí de Pubol"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Progressive Era of the United States",
      "prompt": "Concerning the American Progressive Era, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who introduced the \"New Freedom\" domestic agenda and guided the U.S. through World War One.",
          "answer": "Woodrow Wilson or Thomas Woodrow Wilson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Right for which the Alice Paul-led National Women's Party advocated during the First Wave of Feminism.",
          "answer": [
            "Suffrage",
            "Women's Right to Vote",
            "or Voting"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Chicago settlement house co-founded by Jane Addams.",
          "answer": "Hull House"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for journalists like Ida Tarbell who exposed the excesses of American industry and politics.",
          "answer": [
            "Muckrakers",
            "Muckraking"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Reformist governor of Wisconsin who ran as a Progressive in the Election of 1924.",
          "answer": "Robert La Follette or Robert Marion \"Fighting Bob\" La Follette"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sex educator and eugenicist who popularized the term \"birth control.\"",
          "answer": [
            "Margaret Sanger or Margaret Higgins Sanger",
            "or Margaret Louise Higgins",
            "or Margaret Sanger Slee"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Former vice president who ran as a Progressive in 1948 but only garnered two percent of the national vote.",
          "answer": "Henry Agard Wallace"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor and longtime senator from California who was a vocal opponent of the League of Nations.",
          "answer": "Hiram Johnson or Hiram Warren Johnson"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Balkan Wars in the 20th Century",
      "prompt": "Concerning warfare in the Balkans in the 20th century, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Slavic state which was invaded by Austria-Hungary after the assassination of Franz Ferdinand.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Serbia or Kraljevina Srbija"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of Bosnia & Herzegovina that was the site of \"Sniper Alley\" and a prolonged siege during the 1990s Balkan War.",
          "answer": "Sarajevo or Sarajeva"
        },
        {
          "question": "Technology whose earliest combat use was for scouting was during the First Balkan War.",
          "answer": "Airplanes or Aeroplane"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muslim majority nation in the Western Balkans that became an Italian protectorate during World War Two.",
          "answer": [
            "Albania or Shqipëri",
            "Kingdom of Albania",
            "or Mbretëria Shqiptare"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Informal nickname for the Balkans in the early 20th century due to its political and military volatility.",
          "answer": "Powder keg of Europe or Balkan Powder Keg"
        },
        {
          "question": "King of Greece who led troops in the First Balkan War and was later pressured into exile.",
          "answer": [
            "King Constantine I",
            "Konstantinos I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term used for the Ottoman government that refers to the gate of the Topkapi Palace, which suffered a \"raid\" during the First Balkan War.",
          "answer": "Sublime Porte"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Army of Republica Srpska who was found guilty of genocide for organizing the Srebrenica [sre-brih-NEET-suh]] Massacre.",
          "answer": "Ratko Mladić ] 2021-22 HS National History Bowl Slavery in the Americas"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding slavery in the Americas, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding slavery in the americas, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Nation on Hispaniola established by a successful slave revolt in 1804.",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of Haiti",
            "République d'Haïti",
            "or Repiblik d Ayiti"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Andean empire which used unpaid laborers under the mita system to build Machu Picchu.",
          "answer": [
            "Incan Empire or the Incas",
            "Tawantinsuyu",
            "or Realm of the Four Parts",
            "or Four Parts Together"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Pedro II's daughter, Isabel, passed the Golden Law, abolishing slavery in 1888.",
          "answer": "Empire of Brazil or Império do Brasil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for the section of the Triangular Trade through which slaves were brought to the Americas.",
          "answer": "Middle Passage"
        },
        {
          "question": "Early colonial Spanish labor system which enslaved much of the native population of the Americas.",
          "answer": "Encomienda system"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jamaican runaways who, led by Queen Nanny, resisted British assimilation in two namesake wars.",
          "answer": [
            "Maroons",
            "Maroon Wars"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ceremonial wars fought by the Aztecs to capture slaves for both labor and sacrifice.",
          "answer": [
            "Flower Wars or Flowery Wars",
            "Xōchiyāōyōtl",
            "or Guerra Florida"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Medieval and Early Modern term for fortress-ports where slaves from the interior were held before being shipped overseas.",
          "answer": [
            "Factory or Port Factory",
            "plurals"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This person and Thomas Pitt are depicted having a physical altercation in an illustration by James Gillray titled The Caneing in Conduit Street. W. Kaye Lamb published an annotated edition of a manuscript detailing this explorer’s voyages. (20 pts)",
        "Puget [[PYOO-jet]] Sound, Mount Rainier, and Mount St. Helens were named by this explorer who departed England with the HMS Chatham and HMS (10 pts)",
        "Discovery. For ten points, what British captain led expeditions to explore the Pacific and lends his name to a city in British Columbia?"
      ],
      "answer": "George Vancouver"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An outlaw named Jack Black wrote a memoir about his experiences as one of these people titled You Can’t Win. These people often drew cats and triangles with hands among a series of crypto-signs used as part of their informal communication system. An ethical code (20 pts)",
        "of these people calls on them to take up the least desirable jobs possible in each new town. A willingness to engage in labor was historically seen as a contrast between these people and tramps. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name these migrant workers stereotypically depicted in media carrying their belongings in a bindle."
      ],
      "answer": "Hobo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In her first major work, Hannah Arendt claimed that this agreement was “a turning point in history” since it led to the eschewing of historic customs as a “source of law.” This document calls for the creation of a “public force…instituted for the advantage of all” and the (20 pts)",
        "sixth of its articles claims that “law is the expression of the general will.” Thomas Jefferson consulted on the initial drafts of this document written by the (10 pts)",
        "Marquis de Lafayette. For ten points, name this civil rights document penned during the French Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Declaration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen",
        "Déclaration des Droits de l'Homme et du citoyen de 1789"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Wei Zheng wrote the Book of [this dynasty], which included his own participation in Li Mi's Rebellion. During this dynasty, imperial architect Yuwen Kai [[KYE]] built Daxing [[DAH-SHING]] as an expansion of the Han capital of Xi'an [[ZHE- AHN]]. (20 pts)",
        "A period known as \"The Southern and Northern Dynasties\" was ended after this dynasty's founder, Wen, conquered the Chen Dynasty south of the Yangtze. The (10 pts)",
        "Tang Dynasty succeeded, for ten points, what short-lived imperial dynasty which reunited China in the late 6th century?"
      ],
      "answer": "Sui Dynasty or Suí cháo 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A legend from the Mi’kmaq states that this island was created by the “Great Spirit” when he placed dark red clay in a crescent shape on pink water. Two privateers, Nicholson Broughton and John Selman, raided this island during the American (20 pts)",
        "Revolution. Opened in 1997, the Confederation Bridge connects this province to New Brunswick. The novel Anne of (10 pts)",
        "Green Gables is set in, for ten points, what Canadian island province once part of Acadia?"
      ],
      "answer": "Prince Edward Island"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man once infamously pointed a poker at Karl Popper's face, prompting the latter to describe that as breaking a \"moral rule.\" This thinker negated his own early work, and the entire Vienna Circle School, by developing the concept of \"language games\" (20 pts)",
        "in his second book, Philosophical Investigations. This man never returned to his native Austria following the Anschluss (10 pts)",
        "due to his Jewish ancestry. For ten points, name this student of Bertrand Russell, a transformative Analytic philosopher who wrote Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus."
      ],
      "answer": "Ludwig Wittgenstein or Ludwig Josef Johann Wittgenstein"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of this tribe’s leaders feigned willingness to convert to Christianity in order to launch a surprise attack on English settlers. This tribe, once led by Opechancanough [[oh-puh-CHAN-kuh-noh]], established its main village at (20 pts)",
        "Werowocomoco [[weh-roh-woh-KOH-moh-koh]], and its leaders were known as mamanatowick. One member of this tribe apocryphally saved John (10 pts)",
        "Smith from execution. Pocahontas was a member of, for ten points, what \"confederacy\" of Algonquin tribes from Eastern Virginia?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Powhatan Confederacy",
        "Tsenacommacah",
        "Attanoughkomouck"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A character with this title who experiences peace during the \"Age of Gold\" despairs in Egypt over the sudden drowning of his lover. A character known as the \"arbiter of elegance\" owns a Christian slave girl in a novel set during the reign (20 pts)",
        "of a character with this title. Marguerite Yourcenar [[YOR-seh-nar]] wrote a novel titled the \"Memoirs\" of a person with this title, held by a character who loves the prostitute Calpurnia and hides behind a curtain. (10 pts)",
        "Robert Graves wrote a fictional biography of a character with, for ten points, what title held by Nero and Claudius?"
      ],
      "answer": "Roman Emperor or Emperor of Rome"
    }
  ]
}